<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model 
    href="correspondence%20schema/correspondenceProposal.rng" 
    type="application/xml" 
    schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI 
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
    xmlns:math="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" 
    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Correspondence of Vernon Lee to H.G. Wells</title>
                <author>Lee, Vernon</author><editor>Gagel, Mandy</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>First edition, digital</edition>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transribed by</resp>
                    <name>Mandy Gagel</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded by</resp>
                    <name>Nick Weiler</name>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Loyola University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, Il</pubPlace>
                <date>2012</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Digital born transcritptions of letters from Vernon Lee to H.G. Wells</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="summary">The first known letter to Wells from Lee. 
                    It regards library catalogs and Wells book, Anticipation.</note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <correspDesc>
                    <sender>
                        <persName>Vernon Lee</persName>
                    </sender>
                    <addressee>
                        <persName>H.G. Wells</persName>
                    </addressee>
                    <placeSender>
                        <placeName>IL Palmerino, Florence</placeName>
                    </placeSender>
                    <placeAddressee>
                        <placeName>Wells home, London</placeName>
                    </placeAddressee>
                    <dateSender>
                        <date when="1906-12-18">December 18, 1906</date>
                    </dateSender>
                </correspDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository>Wells Archive at UI, Urbana Champaign</repository>
                    </msIdentifier>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Pilot project for a digital edition of the selected letters of Vernon Lee</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Various explanations here about editing choices we made.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="Lee Letters">
                    <list>
                        <item>letter?
                            <date when="1906-12-18"/>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="draft">
            <change>Yet to certify certain unreadable words</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="letter">
        <body>
            <div type="address">
                <!-- Address is a letterhead, typeface -->
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Il Palmerino</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>S. Gervasio</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Florence.</addrLine>
                </address>
            </div>
            <div type="writingSession">
                <dateline rend="left">Dec. 18 1906</dateline>
            </div>
            <div type="writingSession">
                <salute>Dear Mr Wells - </salute>                
                <p>I have been wanting to write so long, so long; and this letter, which shame
                    at your writing first has makes me begin at an odd moment, will presumably be in and 
                    out of its envelope many times before it gets finished. <hi rend="underline">Shame</hi>, 
                    because it is I who 
                    should have acknowledged your two books, not you my article. I found the <hi rend="underine">
                    Comet</hi> on my return, and have recently only finished it; the American book - I have 
                    not even begun! 
                    My brother has been at the point of death; he seems, after nearly a month’s anxiety, out
                    of momentary danger, but paralysed of one side + miserably weak, like an old, old man. I 
                    am able to do nothing practical (he has a firstrate wife) but the constant running to + fro,
                    + the unavowed anxiety seem to have cut into all my spare time - And somehow I never have 
                    spare time, because I am a bad worker; + worst of all a very, very phenomenally slow reader. 
                    And I cannot <hi rend="unerline">mix</hi> books any more than other folk can mix wines: I must finish what I am reading
                    + then ponderously set to something else - 
                    (damn: the dinnerbell, always a meal: NB <hi rend="underline">no meals or mealtimes after the Comet</hi>)</p> 
                <p>I foresee I shall begin your American book the day after tomorrow; meanwhile, by way of thanks for 
                    it, I am sending you the most delightful thing I can imagine, a letter <hi rend="underline">not in the 
                    least intended for you</hi> - indeed I had a free fight to wrest this very shy old friend’s permission 
                    to send it. She is - 
                    well, judge whether she isn’t exactly the reader one would pray for. Besides this, she is a Cambridge 
                    woman, knows economics <hi rend="underline">very well</hi>; + has seen America from the inside, i.e. all 
                    manner of unlikely places. 
                    I can imagine nothing so pleasing as such pleasure as this letter means.
                    I also venture to send you + your dear wife a facsimile of a drawing by Sargent which, though done 
                    sixteen or seventeen years ago, is still rather like me.</p>
                <p>Well - I shall write to you about the American book, but now, a few words about the <hi rend="underline">Comet</hi>. 
                    (No, not a word more today, for I have a friend with me who is already constitutionally unpunctual, 
                    a “poetic” person +, <hi rend="underline">having been meant myself for a Samurai</hi>, I do not like 
                    keeping my dinner waiting - so, more anon, dear friends) - </p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">Next evening</hi> How much of what I want to say shall I have time to 
                    put down (it is cold as it can be 
                    only in the South, with the wind smiting like a hand full of <hi rend="strikethrough">ice</hi> snow 
                    off the blue + white mountains, + the 
                    stone pine groaning + the olive wood sputtering + smelling delicious) Well! About the <hi rend="underline">Comet
                    </hi>. The 
                    novel part of it seems to me very fine in quality. (And, is it rude to say so? far finer as a [?] 
                    literary expression than any of your previous books) - the quality of Mr Lewisham, a sort of 
                    contained, overallish passionateness which, just because <hi rend="underline">it is of the whole bodily life</hi>
                    , heart <hi rend="underline">lungs + muscle</hi>, 
                    is always human, never - well, animal. Do you understand? Of course, for you have done this feat 
                    yourself. And all the tragedy of the poor odious foolish boy is direct + as the Germans say 
                    “packs one” - Moreover, the criticism of the present state of things is just + scathing - I think 
                    this sort of holding the mirror up to the tolerated unnecessary follies of our days (the splendid 
                    passage on the Boer + German wars, + many others) is one of the most useful things a writer 
                    can do.</p> 
                <p>It is the mission of the prophet to use the future (of course no real future ever) to preach at the 
                    present from; + what we want most is the habit of considering the present as a [line missing, see 
                    original] its most successful details as mere momentary stop gaps: the past, with all its great gifts, 
                    has left us a Pandora’s nuisance in the shape of <hi rend="underline">acquiescence</hi> + the 
                    belief that what <hi rend="underline">has been must be</hi>, 
                    whereas nine times out of ten t’is the other way on.</p>
                <p>So, I like the first part of the <hi rend="underline">Comet</hi> extremely. Of course you yourself 
                    must feel what everyone tells 
                    <hi rend="underline">me</hi>, that the 2d part is a falling off. The actual meteorological business is really tremendously 
                    fine (the comet + its vapours with the naval battle) - But then one comes to understand + to care. 
                    This is probably inevitable. <hi rend="strikethrough">Once</hi> You <hi rend="underline">yourself cannot</hi> 
                    know <hi rend="underline">what kind of change</hi> the <hi rend="underline">green vapours have wrought</hi>. 
                    Have vicious possibilities vanished? fools become wise, etc? etc. Tis an inconceivable 
                    thing; but quite worth filling in for the sake of the frame work it affords you. Here again, the 
                    useful + (to me, but not many others) interesting work of suggesting change. The mischief is that 
                    you cannot really tell us enough of that change. Your logical premise is false: i.e. people become 
                    sensible + good while surrounded by the things of folly + selfishness. There are some things which 
                    have provoked discussion in my + I suppose many other circles. Are you throwing dust in our eyes for 
                    fear of the [?] <hi rend="underline">young person’s</hi> parents, or do y are you at a loss how the question of sexual love etc. 
                    will evolve after the green vapours? <hi rend="strikethrough">Do you</hi></p>
                <p>Like the woman in Dumas’ play “Vous pouvez me le dire puisque je suis une femme d’esprit” - <hi rend="strikethrough">i.e.</hi>
                    that is, 
                    if you have anything to say, + do not merely drop the “cloud” - over the future of love as Ruskin did 
                    over the past of glaciers. I can imagine two readings of the suggestion your postscript contains.
                    1o When people shall have become morally better; a great many arrangements, including <hi rend="underline">ménage à quatre</hi>
                    , 
                    free love etc. etc., which would entail monstrous disorder nowadays if avowedly tolerated, would become 
                    purely personal questions, offspring + inheritance etc being settled for, and wholesomeness of 
                    individuals looking after the business.
                    2do When people shall have come to live mere natural lives, certain possibilities, certain deviations 
                    + scissions of feeling which our imperfection excludes as <hi rend="underline">morbid, [unwholesome]</hi> 
                    etc. will become 
                    possible; and among these [?] of the emotional possibilities, platonic love as a reality; even as 
                    un-sexual love between near blood relations has become possible in consequence of the suppression 
                    of incest - 
                    <hi rend="underline">Now</hi>, which, or any of these? You are English, + perhaps my 
                    Latin decency or indecency astonishes + 
                    abashes you. Anyhow, I feel that you, like me, believe that there may be surprises in store for the 
                    future: the surprise of much becoming permissible; only the “green vapours” will not come unless these 
                    future permissible things are meanwhile forbidden - (But <hi rend="strikethrough">not</hi> I don’t choose to be forbidden these plain 
                    questions) - </p>
                
                <p>23d</p> 
                 <p>Dear Mr Wells - This letter is already too long by half, + it is not half finished, so I send it off. 
                    And add that since two days I have been reading your <hi rend="underline">entrancing America</hi>. 
                    You have never done anything 
                    so good. I am only at the 3d chapter, + if I have time to write, + you to read, I will write again 
                    when I have finished it. I feel as if it had been <hi rend="underline">written expressly for me</hi>
                    , + this is probably the 
                    feeling of each of your intelligent + willing readers. All my friend writer is absolutely what I think.
                    Give my love - give this letter - to your dear wife. I am always so grateful for your quick, light 
                    cordiality towards a rather disputative stranger. When you have time let me know about the Fabians, 
                    whether I can join.</p>
                <closer>Yours sincerely <signed><hi rend="underline">V. Paget</hi></signed>
                </closer>                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>